Álvaro Rondinelli Mesquita da Silva

rondinellimesquitas@gmail.com +55 85 9 9230 5400 Fortaleza, Ceará, Brazil github.com/rondymesquita

SUMMARY

Experience with web and mobile development, with knowledge in web design. Experience with web and mobile test automation and continuous integration. Currently works as software developer and test analyst at Instituto Atlântico, Fortaleza, on research projects for HP (Hewlett-Packard Inc).

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer (December 2013 – Present) Instituto Atlântico - http://www.atlantico.com.br Fortaleza, Ceará, Brazil

Analysis and development of software for research projects of technology. Development, unit and functional testing, automated tests for web and mobile, guided by quality requirements, code review, coding standards, continuous integration and agile methodologies.

HP Enterprise Project

- [2018 2020] Developer of a software consisted by front end and back end services. Front end consists in a Single Page Application built with VueJS, using JWT token to access back end service. Back end consists in a REST API built with NodeJS, accessing multiples services as MySQL database and AWS S3. Some features required design and investigation, proof of concepts development, leading to creating diagrams and proposals to solve problems, having technical discussion with team and stakeholders to decide best approach. Using Jenkins as CI/CD tool and Docker as container tool. Project was deployed to production and archived 1 million of jobs made by real users. Project required strict code structure and standards to be followed as design patterns, code review, unit, functional and end to end tests. Also, working with the automation test team in order to build an architecture to an End to End testing solution in order to cover entire software functionality using Robot Framework to run tests to multiples platforms. Agile methods with SCRUM and XP. Technologies: VueJS, ExpressJS, NodeJS, ES6, SASS, Node package manager (NPM), Linux, Git, AWS, CI/CD, Docker, Shell Script, Cypress for functional front end tests, Mocha for back end tests, Robot Framework (Appium and Selenium) for End to End tests.
- **[2017]** Developer and tester of a software of gather information using python and storing it on AWS S3. Using AWS Athena to consume this data and creating custom queries. Agile methods as SCRUM and XP. Technologies: Python, Python Unittest framework, Git, AWS S3, AWS Athena, Shell script,
- **[2016-2017]** Developer of a set of Golang microservices for network management running inside docker containers and managed by a Kubernetes cluster. Technologies: Golang, Git, Docker, Kubernetes, Shell script.

– [2016] Developer of solutions for network management. Developing Restful API running in virtual embedded systems using Python as main language. Network management using Ansible. Development of Ansible modules using Python. Code review using Github Enterprise and Git. Agile methods as SCRUM and XP. Technologies: Python, Ansible, Git, Linux, Shell script, Docker.

HP Inc Project

- **[2015]** Developer and tester of a software, using manual and automated testing techniques. Developing automated tests using C#/.Net, tracking quality metrics of software using HP ALM (Application Lifecycle Management) software. Making code review using Gerrit and tracking with a customized continuous integration tool. Development of features of a SPA (Single Page Application) using Backbone and JQuery JavaScript frameworks, SASS and QUnit. Using of agile methods as SCRUM and Kanban. Technologies: C#/.NET, Backbone, Jquery, Git, SASS.
- **[2013-2014]** Developer and tester of a Java web application using Spring MVC, Spring, JQuery, KnockoutJS, using Maven as dependency management and automation tool. Development of web test automation using Capybara and Cucumber ruby frameworks, with TDD and BDD techniques and unit tests using JUnit and Mockito. Development of a mobile application using Android and Gradle, with mobile test automation using Calabash ruby framework. Performing code review using Gitlab tool and TeamCity continuous integration/delivery tool. Technologies: Java, Spring, Jquery, KnockoutJS, Maven, JUnit, Mockito, Android, Capybara, Calabash, Cucumber, Gradle, TeamCity.

Instituto Atlântico – Internal Project – Coach of web and mobile testing using Java platform, Selenium, Appium, CucumberJVM. Using Maven as dependency management tool and Jenkins for continuous integration.

College Lecturer (May 2015)

Faculdade Vale do Salgado - http://www.fvs.edu.br/ Icó, Ceará, Brazil

Disciplines:

Software Verification and Validation – Post-Graduation course of Software Engineering

- Knowledge base of Software Testing using Agile Approach
- Material in Portuguese: https://goo.gl/al3af0

Software Developer (March 2012 – July 2013)

Nooclix Software Factory Juazeiro do Norte, Ceará, Brazil

Analysis and development of solutions of e-commerce and management software, using JavaEE, Google Web Toolkit (GWT), GXT, Spring, VRaptor, JavaScript, Android, PostgreSQL and PHP. Worked as web designer developing websites using Wordpress platform. Creation of web prototypes and icons using Photoshop and CorelDraw.

Project E-commerce – Web store application using VRaptor Java framework, Spring for dependency injection, including concepts of restful API and Maven for build and dependency management. Unit test using JUnit. Creation of user interfaces using JSP,

JQuery and CSS using Bootstrap CSS framework. PostgreSQL for database and Hibernate as persistence layer.

Agile Room Manager – Web application made with Vraptor Java framework, Spring and Jquery Mobile framework for user interfaces. Maven for build and dependency management. Unit test using JUnit. PostgreSQL for database and Hibernate as persistence layer.

EDUCATION

Bachelor's Degree in Information Systems (January 2010 – December 2013)

Faculdade de Juazeiro do Norte Juazeiro do Norte, Ceará, Brazil

Relevant productions

Good practices of websites development: An overview of how to develop a website, cycles and what should be considered to create a good website https://goo.gl/GqYwVe

Development of mobile applications using JQuery Mobile: A step by step of how to create mobile interfaces using Jquery Mobile framework https://goo.gl/3l8gVR

Final paper: The use of the agile methodologies SCRUM and Extreme Programming in support of knowledge management in the software development https://goo.gl/OhVlbc

Post-Graduated in Development of Mobile Applications (October 2013 – December 2014) Faculdade de Juazeiro do Norte Juazeiro do Norte, Ceará, Brazil

Final paper: The use of mobile applications in support of the practices of agile methodologies SCRUM and Extreme Programming https://goo.gl/0cuAQh

PERSONAL OPEN PROJECTS

PhoenixJS: Content Management System written in AngularJS (v1), including concepts of Single Page Application, using only front end technologies: AngularJS, Karma, JasmineJS, Gulp, Bower.

https://goo.gl/OvdeP6

Selenium Screenshooter: Java library to use with Selenium Java, that performs screen captures of web page and verify layout, color and element position, comparing with previously saved webpage state. Enables automated testing of user interface. Technologies: Java, Selenium, Maven, JUnit.

https://goo.gl/qG3pF7